<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id="ximian-connnector-booking">
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Direct Booking of Resource Calendars</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>3</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo>XIMIAN-CONNECTOR Library</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv></refnamediv>

<para>
"Direct booking" is the ability to directly add appointments to the
calendar of an Exchange "user" that represents a resource. ("Resource"
almost always means a conference room, but in theory could also be a
video projector, white board, or anything else reservable.)
</para>

<para>
Connector's implementation of this functionality is designed to be
basically identical to <application>Outlook</application>'s.
</para>

<refsect2>
<title>Creating a Resource</title>

<para>
Any Exchange account can be a resource. Nothing special needs to be
done in Exchange or Active Directory. There are three properties,
stored on the account's <link linkend="freebusy">personal free/busy
message</link> that control whether or not
<application>Outlook</application> and
<application>Evolution</application> treat it as a resource:
</para>

<variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
	<term><literal>PR_PROCESS_MEETING_REQUESTS</literal></term>
	<listitem><para>
	If <literal>TRUE</literal>, then the account is a resource.
	</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
	<term><literal>PR_DECLINE_RECURRING_MEETING_REQUESTS</literal></term>
	<listitem><para>
	If <literal>TRUE</literal>, the resource cannot be booked for
	recurring events.
	</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
	<term><literal>PR_DECLINE_CONFLICTING_MEETING_REQUESTS</literal></term>
	<listitem><para>
	If <literal>TRUE</literal>, the resource cannot be double-booked.
	</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>
Connector doesn't currently provide any way to set these properties on
a mailbox. (<application>Outlook</application> does.)
</para>

<para>
Of course, to be able to act as a resource, the account's Calendar
must be writable by other users. (And the properties on the free/busy
message must be readable as well. If you use the Delegates dialog in
either <application>Outlook</application> or
<application>Evolution</application>, it will make sure the free/busy
message is readable to any user who can read the Calendar.)
</para>

</refsect2>


<refsect2>
<title>Booking a Resource</title>

<para>
<application>Outlook</application>'s convention is that direct booking
happens when all of the following are true:
</para>

<orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>
    An <application>Exchange</application> user is added to the
    meeting with an attendee type of <literal>RESOURCE</literal>.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
    That user has the <literal>PR_PROCESS_MEETING_REQUESTS</literal>
    property set.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
    The user creating the meeting has permission to create the
    appointment in the resource user's Calendar.
    </para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
If any of these criteria are not met, then it
<emphasis>silently</emphasis> falls back to normal mail-based
scheduling. (Among other things, this allows you to set up a resource
such that some users can book it directly, but if anyone else tries
to, it will just send a meeting request to that account, which can
then be accepted or rejected manually by a secretary.)
</para>

<para>
If all the criteria are met, but the meeting must be rejected because
of the settings of the
<literal>PR_DECLINE_RECURRING_MEETING_REQUESTS</literal> or
<literal>PR_DECLINE_CONFLICTING_MEETING_REQUESTS</literal> properties,
then <application>Outlook</application> will pop up an error dialog
explaining the problem, and refuse to save/send the meeting request.
</para>

<para>
If the resource can be booked, then <application>Outlook</application>
will update the meeting request to show that the resource has accepted
it, save that meeting request in the resource's calendar, and then
send that meeting request to all of the remaining users (but NOT the
resource) by mail.
</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2>
<title>Cancelation</title>

<para>
If you cancel a meeting that has a booked resource,
<application>Outlook</application> <emphasis>does not</emphasis>
remove the event from the resource's calendar. Instead, it prepends
"Cancelled: " to the event's summary and changes its
<literal>TRANSP</literal> property to <literal>TRANSPARENT</literal>
so that it no longer shows up as busy. This leaves the original event
in the calendar, for record-keeping purposes, but allows a new event
to use the resource instead.
</para>

</refsect2>

</refentry>